right over here the 3d setup as you can see right
here we have a representation of like a room
and to start setting up our fixtures we need to
start by going into the setup menu right here
if you look at the positions right now you have
pan and you have tilt as soon as you enter the
setup then it changes to position x y and z and
rotation x y and z and again if you exit the setup
it goes back to normal but to start setting up
your 3d view you need to go into the setup first
and activate that right now we have our four
groups up here let's just select our vipers
and as you can see over here this small yellow
square down here and that that's actually because
all our fixtures are below the floor right now
what we can do is start by raising them up into
the air and you can simply push this one you can
you can dial this one and that will move them up
up or down or you can just push it and say six
please that will put it at six meters height
then we need to push it back because it's it's
on our zero point right now so if we push that
one and say okay we need this in the depth of
six meters once again press six and it goes
back into the 3d world here right here we have
position x and what we can do here is we can move
move it from side to side which is great except
for we are moving all 12 fixtures right now
there's actually 12 fixtures selected but they're
right on top of each other so you can only see one
so we want to reset this one to zero and then
we're going to go over to our align tool over
here and if you push that once you will have
this dash here and then when you start dialing
this in you will see it spaces them out right
now we are at six meters so this is from center
this is center so this is minus six meters in one
direction and plus six meters in another direction
which gives us a total of 12 meters so right
now they are positioned from -6 to 6 meters here
6 meters back into the 3d world and 6
meters up into the air in the 3d world
so that would be our vipers let's push this one
down here called at and then you can simply clear
three times and that will release all the fixtures
then we take our auras we do the same thing we
find the z-axis or the z-axis and
we put them the last ones we put in
six meters so we put these ones in six point
five meters just a little bit above the
other ones and then we move it back to 5.5
meters so we space them half a meter apart
and then we do the same thing we align and we
start dialing the the knob here and that would
again put it to six meters in each direction what
we can do right now is because i don't know if we
if we started the spacing uh the wrong way
so what we can do now is show label on body
that will show that we have 601 2 3 4 5 all
the way up to 12 but our vipers is upside down
or it should be the other way around i want the
number one down here what we can do now is select
all our wipers oh sorry we need to clear first
select our wipers select the align tool again
and then start dialing in here and we simply
go to center and continue the other way
and we once again hit if we can hit it six
meters in each direction it's kind of hard to hit
oh come on
there we go six meters in each direction um so
that's how it works it's it's very very very cool
that you can show the label on the body and you
can you can actually show the label on the spot as
well if i take all my vipers go into the ad here
and say add full you can actually see the numbers
on the floor as well where each cone is hitting
but i don't like that that's not necessary so we
can just turn this one off so there we go i just
keep the label on the body right now because we
need to align the atomics as well and the dimmers
as well so select the atomics put them up into
maybe seven meters and push them back to maybe
five meters and then once again we align it and we
space them out the way we want it like this maybe
five and a half minus two positive five five and
a half meters we clear that and we go into dimmer
and we do exactly the same thing again so we go to
7.5 meters maybe then we
push it back to 4.5 meters
and then we space it like last time
there we go and we see if we can hit the
six meter mark again there we go so right now
we actually set up all our fixtures in the 3d
world if we clear this this out here and we
turn off the label here you can say all vipers
add full all auras at full all atomics and they
will probably not show up correct because it's
a strobe and then all dimmers at full so there
we go that's the fixtures we patched last time
after we set up our 3d view and set
all our fixtures up in the 3d world
we just have a brief look in some of the options
in here you have some selection modes we have some
labels on the spot as i showed you some labels on
the body which can help you to navigate around you
have some quality body quality to to to basically
be nicer to the computer if it needs to render the
the view you have some beam quality here as well
depending on how much detail you want to see
stage view some front view you can change these
ones to to all kinds of different views but that's
for a different tutorial if you press the ma logo
up here there's some other options the first one
down here you see the rendering miscellaneous
label and quality rendering is where you can tweak
like the beams and the spot and the ambient light
for instance if you want to turn that up or you
want to turn it down you can do that right here
and some other stuff go play with it and see if
if there's any stuff in here that that suits you
better the miscellaneous one as you can see up
here i have frames per second if you push that one
it goes away i like to have it on to see how much
load i'm putting on the computer itself you can
go into a wireframe a wireframe view which will
make much less load on the computer
this is how it looked on the GrandMA2
but but now we actually have a much better view
in the 3d built into the built into the GrandMA 3
the 3d priority if you are on a real lighting
desk and doing a big show a real granite may full
size or light or whatever you would probably not
want the 3d priority to be on the desk you wanted
to have it on a separate machine a laptop or a
stationary computer somewhere so but here you can
simply go in and say okay i have 3d priority and
they didn't it would prioritize the the the power
to to do all the rendering but uh not necessarily
a good idea to do it on the desk itself if you
are running larger shows some shading options
some touch modes options i mean you have to
play around with this to see exactly what it is
you what it is you need and what it is you like
some labels again label and body label on spot you
can add different things that that's under labels
like patch information names and stuff
like that but again up to you what you
want to do last time the quality render
lights yellow pictures again play with it
see if if you can have any fun with it but that's
basically a very simple setup of our 3d GrandMA 3
in this tutorial thank you very much for
watching this video and if you find any
value in it please please give the video a
like or maybe even subscribe to our channel
but i hope to see you next time thank you
very much for watching this episode bye